Guide to the Nell Irvin Painter Papers, 1793-2021 and undated, bulk 1876-2007 RL.00990
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Correspondence Series, 1862-2008 and undated, bulk 1970-2007, 98 boxes
  - Student/Candidate Files Subseries, 1862-2006 and undated, bulk 1988-2000, 13 boxes
    - Ouellet, Nelson, 1995 Sept.-1999 Feb. (Box 77)
    - P, 1997 Nov. and undated (Box 77)
    - Pagán, Eduardo, 1991 Jan.-2000 Jan., 3 folders (Box 78)
    - Peiss, Kathy, 1996 Feb.-Mar. (Box 78)
    - Gail Pellett Productions, 1996 Jan.-May (Box 78)
    - Pemberton, Gayle, 1994 Feb.-1996 Oct. and undated (Box 78)
    - Powell, Carolyn, 1994 July-Sept. (Box 78)
    - Prakash, Gyan, 1992 Jan. (Box 78)
    - Pratt, Robert, 1990 Sept.-1991 Jan. (Box 78)
    - Price, Sally, 1991 Feb. (Box 78)
    - Quarles, Ruth, 1967 Feb., 1998 Jan. and undated (Box 78)
    - R, 1996 Oct.-2000 Jan. (Box 78)
    - Rachleff, Melissa, 1994 Feb.-July and undated (Box 78)
    - Reed, Linda, 1992 Mar.-1997 Mar. (Box 78)
    - Reiss, Benjamin, undated (Box 78)
    - Ricketts, Anayansi, 1994 Oct.-Dec. (Box 78)
    - Roberts, Blain, 1995-Oct.-1997 Dec. (Box 78)
    - Roberts, Sam, 1996 Feb.-2000 Apr. (Box 79)
    - Robinson, Jackie, 1995 Mar.-1996 June (Box 79)
    - Rooks, Noliwe, 1996 Dec.-2000 Jan. (Box 79)
    - Schechter, Patty, 1990 Feb.-1993 Oct., 2 folders (Box 79)
    - Sheidley, Nathaniel, 1995 Oct. (Box 79)
    - Straker, Ian, 1992 Spring-1996 Oct., 2 folders (Box 79)
    - Sweet, John, 1990 May-1999, 4 folders (Box 79)
    - Taylor, Marie, 1996 Apr.-July (Box 80)
    - Thompson, Heather, 1993 Aug.-1995 Sept., 1996-1999, 2 folders (Box 80)
    - Walker, Barbara, 1995 June-1996 Mar. (Box 80)
    - White, Deborah Gray, 1993 Aug. and undated, 2 folders (Box 80)
    - Yu, Henry, 1991 May-1993 Oct., 1997, 2 folders (Box 80)
    - Wilson, James, 1998-2000, 6 folders (Box 80)
    - Yellin, Erc, 2004-2006 (Box 258)
    - General Files (Box 80)
      - Course evaluations, 1994 June (Box 80)
      - Graduate students and prospective graduate students, 1991-1996, 3 folders (Box 80)
      - Juniors, 1994-1995 (Box 80)
      - Recommendations, 1980-2000, Folders 1-2 of 19 (Box 80)
      - Recommendations, 1980-2000, Folders 3-12 of 19 (Box 81)
      - Recommendations, 1980-2000, Folders 13-19 of 19 (Box 82)
      - Senior theses, 1993-1996, 2 folders (Box 82)
      - Student inquiries, 1993-1995 (Box 82)
      - Students, 1995 (Box 82)
  - Nellie Y. McKay Subseries (CLOSED), 1977-2005, 8 boxes
    Correspondence between Painter and Nellie Y. McKay, who met in 1969 when both were first-year graduate students at Harvard (Painter in history, McKay in English). McKay went on to become a professor of American and African-American Literature and published important works on Toni Morrison and Jean Toomer among other writers. She spent most of her career at the University of Wisconsin-Madison. Bulk of subseries consists of correspondence from McKay, but several years into the sequence many copies of Painter's letters begin to appear, too. Letters cover the personal and professional lives of both women, enriched by a variety of attachments, including drafts of writings, newspaper clippings about their careers and current events, promotional materials, snapshots, and sometimes copies of correspondence with third parties. Arranged chronologically, although researchers should note that Painter's original labeling on the folders is not always complete. Often the correspondence inside the folders covers a longer span of months than she indicated; this has been amended in pencil, but items were not shifted between or within folders, so contiguous folders should be examined for particular weeks or months.
    Conditions Governing Access note
    [CLOSED: Items in the Nellie Y. McKay Subseries are closed until forty years from the original date of creation of each item.]
    - 1977 Aug.-1982 May, 6 folders (Box 82)
    - 1982 Mar.-1985 June, 10 folders (Box 83)
    - 1985 June-1987 Feb., 8 folders (Box 84)
    - 1987 Feb.-1988 Sept., 11 folders (Box 85)
    - 1988 Fall-1990 Jan., 11 folders (Box 86)
    - 1989 Nov.-1991 Apr., 12 folders (Box 87)
    - 1991 Mar.-1992 June, 12 folders (Box 88)
    - 1992 June-2005 July, 12 folders (Box 89)
- Writings and Research Series, 1793, 1835-2007 and undated, bulk 1876-2004, 66 boxes
  Writings, research materials, notes, and correspondence that document the genesis of Painter's major books and many articles, essays, and reviews. Contains significant amounts of correspondence with publishers, sources, and colleagues; articles and talks sent by colleagues; and copious notes and numerous photocopies of primary sources, including newspapers and government records. There are also many drafts of Painter's talks and writings, including manuscripts, typescripts, and printer's proofs.
  Arranged in eight subseries, the first six of which are based on five of Painter's major books: Exodusters: Black Migration to Kansas After Reconstruction (1976); The Narrative of Hosea Hudson: His Life as a Negro Communist in the South (1979); Sojourner Truth, A Life, A Symbol (1996); Standing at Armageddon: The United States, 1877-1919 (1987); Creating Black Americans: African American History and Its Meanings, 1619 to the Present (2005); and The History of White People (2010). Each subseries is further divided into three subgroups, Correspondence, Drafts, and Research Materials; see specific subseries notes for further detail about the arrangement and content of these categories for each book. Materials unrelated to these five books--or whose relationship to them could not be established--have been placed in one of the final two subseries, Other Research Topics or Writings by Others. Note that while all the subseries contain writings by other authors, the main criterion for placing materials in Writings by Others is that the folder contains only such writing. If a folder contains Painter's notes and commentary in addition to writings by other authors or contains works by multiple authors that Painter gathered under a topical heading, then they are placed in one of the first five subseries or in Other Research Topics. This subseries, the largest in the Writings and Research Series, is further divided into subgroups by topic; see its subseries note for further details on its arrangement.
  Several types of documents that appear in this series are supported by related material in other series. Three are of particular note: correspondence, addresses, and writing by other authors. Much correspondence appears in various subseries in Writings and Research, and it addresses many of the same topics broached in the Correspondence Series; it can be searched alphabetically or chronologically according to the arrangement of the particular subseries. Drafts of Painter's addresses and articles have generally been placed in the Writings and Research Series--especially in the Other Research Topics Subseries--if the folders consist mainly of substantive drafts of the work or research on it; but other versions may also appear in the Engagements Subseries of the Professional Service Series. Finally, a substantial amount of writing by other authors, especially when those authors were current or former students or advisees of Painter's, appears in two other series. Most such material appears as attachments to letters in the Student/Candidate Files Subseries of the Correspondence Series; a smaller amount, in the form of drafts unattached to correspondence, appears at the end of the Teaching Materials Series, Academic Files Subseries.
  As mentioned in the Collection Overview, the dating of folder titles is of particular note in this series due to the large volume of photocopies and microform printouts of archival and historical material. If the folder contains Painter's notes or quotations from a primary source, the date corresponds to the time Painter worked on the subject. If the folder contains an original source or photocopy of one (almost always the latter), the date corresponds to when the intellectual content was originally produced or published.
  - Creating Black Americans Subseries, 1968, 2001-2006, 2 boxes
    Documents Painter's survey of African American history, which uses black American art to illustrate the narrative. Consists mainly of typescript drafts of several chapters. Arranged alphabetically in the categories of Correspondence and Research, chronologically in Drafts.
    - Correspondence (Box 90)
      - Book reviews, 2002 Feb. (Box 90)
      - Borland Bruce and Barbara Miller, 2001-2002 (Box 90)
      - Dooley, Emily, 2001 June 6 (Box 90)
      - Family, circa 2001 (Box 90)
    - Drafts
      - 2001 Sept. 3, Chapter 5 (Box 90)
      - 2002 Oct. 26, Chapter 8, lecture at University of Houston (Box 90)
      - 2003, Chapters 3 and 8, text and illustrations (Box 90)
      - 2003 Oct. 25- 2003 Dec. 17, Chapters 1-15, edited typescript, 5 folders (Box 90)
      - 2003 Dec. 17, Epilogue, edited typescript (Box 259)
      - 2004 Jan.-Mar. Preface, 2 folders (Box 259)
      - 2004 July 30, Chapter 1 (Box 259)
      - 2005, Mock-up of cover (Box 259)
      - 2006 Mar., page proofs (3 folders) (Box 259)
    - Research
      - Davis, Thadious, Introduction, Quicksand. Penguin Classics, 2001 (Box 259)
      - Review of Sterling Stuckey's Going Through the Storm: The Influence of African American Art in History, 2001 (Box 259)
      - Grove African-American Art Pre-1920, 2001 Oct. (Box 259)
      - Hartwell, Peggy, slides, 2001 (Box 259)
      - Oral History Interview with Jacob Lawrence, 1968 (Box 259)
  - Exodusters Subseries, 1858-1996 and undated, bulk 1876-1884 and 1968-1976, 9 boxes
    Materials have been organized into three subgroups, Correspondence, Drafts, and Research Materials. Correspondence also includes book reviews. The Drafts subgroup consists of typescripts and printer's proofs. Related writings and speeches by Painter are organized with the research materials. The materials in the Correspondence and Research Materials subgroups are arranged alphabetically, while those in the Drafts subgroup are arranged chronologically. Because they lack precise date information, three typescripts and three printer's proofs have been labeled A to C. This labeling does not reflect any chronological ordering among those documents. In the Research Materials subgroup, articles by Painter are indicated by (NIP); writings by others are listed alphabetically by last name. The designations "(d)" and "(w)" she occasionally places after the names of certain newspapers indicate whether it was a daily or weekly publication, respectively.
    - Correspondence (Box 91)
      - 1976-1977, 1980 (Box 91)
      - Book reviews, 1976-1977 (Box 91)
      - Book reviews, 1977-1978 (Box 91)
      - Book reviews, 1977-1979 (Box 91)
      - Candidate statement, correspondence, and research materials, 1971 and undated (Box 91)
      - Harvard University Press, manuscript guidelines with notes, undated (Box 91)
      - McGraw-Hill, Exodusters, 1996 (Box 91)
      - Photographs and negatives, 1877-1884 and undated, 13 items (Box 91)
      - University of Kansas Press, Exodusters, 2nd ed., 1985 (Box 91)
      - University of Kansas Press, 2nd ed., and drafts of Preface, 1985-1986 (Box 91)
      - Washington Post editorial, 1977 Feb. 19; New York Times, 1977 (Box 91)
    - Drafts
      - 1973, Kansas Fever Exodus and Millennial chapter originals (Box 91)
      - circa 1974
        - Introductory chapter-notes (Box 91)
        - Typescript A, 2 folders (Box 91)
        - Typescript B, 3 folders (Box 91)
        - Typescript C, 4 folders (Box 92)
      - circa 1975, Introduction, manuscript (Box 92)
      - circa 1976
        - Proof A, 5 folders (Box 92)
        - Proof B, 3 folders (Box 92)
        - Proof C, 2 folders (Box 93)
    - Research Materials
      - A.M.E., Methodist Publishing Board, and Southern Baptists, 1968-1972 and undated (Box 93)
      - American Colonization Society
        - Abraham Cashaw, undated (Box 93)
        - Correspondence and testimony of Henry Adams, 1879 and undated (Box 93)
        - James Green (Houston) Texas material, undated (Box 93)
        - Letters from Kansas, undated (Box 93)
        - Liberia Exodus, Joint Stock Steamship Co., Charleston, S.C., undated (Box 93)
        - Library of Congress, 1882-1883 (Box 93)
        - Library of Congress, 1883-1885 (Box 93)
        - Undated (Box 93)
      - American Missionary Association Papers-Kansas, undated (Box 93)
      - The American Negro Historical Society, Historical Society of Pennsylvania, undated (Box 93)
      - Benjamin Pap Singleton, (NIP), 1975, and Walter Fleming, 1909 (Box 93)
      - Bibliographical material, Tennessee, 1964, 1970, and undated (Box 93)
      - Blake, Lee Ella: The Great Exodus of 1879 and 1880 to Kansas, 1942 (Box 93)
      - Bobbs-Merrill Reprint Series in Black Studies, 1952-1969 (Box 93)
      - Bogue, Allan G.: Money at Interest, undated (Box 93)
      - Cartwright, Joseph Howard: The Negro in Tennessee Politics, 1880-1891, unpublished masters thesis, Vanderbilt, 1968 (Box 93)
      - Chicago Daily Inter Ocean, 1878-1879 (Box 93)
      - Chicago Daily Inter Ocean, 1879-1880, notes, circa 1971 (Box 93)
      - Chicago Tribune, 1879, 2 folders (Box 93)
      - Chicago Tribune (d), notes and photocopies, 1879 and undated (Box 93)
      - Chirenje, J. Mutero: A History of Northern Botswana..., 1975 (Box 93)
      - Christian Recorder, Mother Bethel (A.M.E.) Church, undated (Box 93)
      - The Colored Exodus, Harper's Weekly, 1879 (Box 93)
      - Colored Relief Board, St. Louis, undated (Box 94)
      - Congressional Record, Windom resolution and debates, 1879 (Box 94)
      - Contemporary reactions, undated (Box 94)
      - Correspondence to Kansas Governor, 1879, records of Kansas Freedmen's Relief Association, 1879-1880 (Box 94)
      - Correspondence to Kansas governor, 1879-1882 (Box 94)
      - Demography, 1880-1883 and undated (Box 94)
      - Editorial reactions, undated (Box 94)
      - Essay on Senate hearings concerning the Exodus, (NIP), undated (Box 94)
      - Excerpts from newspapers, Senate reports, and Department of Justice files, undated (Box 94)
      - Exodusters, First Annual Report of the Bureau of Labor and Industrial Statistics, State of Kansas, 1886 (Box 94)
      - Exodus to Kansas, (NIP), Encyclopedia of Southern History, circa 1975; and related correspondence, 1975 (Box 94)
      - Fisk University Library, undated (Box 94)
      - Fisk University Special Collections-Tennessee State Library and Archives-AME Methodist Publishing Board-Baptist Sunday School Union, undated (Box 94)
      - Fort Scot and Topeka (Kansas) Colored Citizen (w), undated (Box 94)
      - Fort Scot (Kansas) Colored Citizen, 1878 (Box 94)
      - Garvin's Pap Singleton, JiNH, 1948 (Box 94)
      - Hinds County Gazette, Raymond, Miss. (w.), 1877-1879 (Box 94)
      - Howard University, Moorland-Spingarn Collection, Bruce Papers, undated (Box 94)
      - Howard University, Moorland-Spingarn Collection, undated (Box 94)
      - Interior Department, Census Office, Report on cotton production in the United States, 1884 (Box 94)
      - Kansas and the West, 1968 and undated, 2 folders (Box 94)
      - The Kansas Fever Exodus of 1879, (NIP), 1973; and draft, Millenarian Aspects of the Exodus to Kansas of 1879, (NIP), undated (Box 94)
      - Kansas State Historical Society
        - 1880-1951 (Box 94)
        - Governor's papers and newspapers, undated (Box 95)
        - Missouri-Pacific Railroad, 1879-1880, 2 folders (Box 95)
        - (Topeka), Governor St. John, correspondence, 1879 (Box 95)
      - Kansas to Liberia, undated (Box 95)
      - Liberian Exodus, 1880 and 1994 (Box 95)
      - Library of Congress, undated (Box 95)
      - Louisiana parishes, undated (Box 95)
      - Louisiana State University, undated (Box 95)
      - M.A. theses and Ph.D. dissertations on Exodus, 1935-1967 (Box 95)
      - Microfilm requests and Census register, 1971 (Box 95)
      - Millenarian Aspects of the Exodus to Kansas of 1879, (NIP), 1976 (Box 95)
      - Millennial Aspects of the Exodus to Kansas of 1879, (NIP), draft, undated; book reviews, 1977; research materials, undated (Box 95)
      - Minnesota Historical Society, William Windom Papers, 1879 (Box 95)
      - Miscellaneous periodical notes-theses, undated (Box 95)
      - Mississippi Legal Library, 1879, 1928, and 1972 (Box 95)
      - Mississippi materials, undated (Box 95)
      - Natchez Daily Democrat, 1878 June-1879 July (Box 95)
      - National Archives I, 1878 and undated (Box 95)
      - National Archives II, photocopies, mostly Justice Department, 1876-1881, bulk 1876-1878, 4 folders (Box 96)
      - Nebraska State Historical Society, Lincoln, Neb., 1965 and undated (Box 96)
      - Negro Clippings, vols. 1-6 and some vol. 7; Rust scrapbook, etc., Kansas State Historical Society, 1937-1943, and notes, undated (Box 96)
      - Negro population, 1790-1910, undated (Box 96)
      - New Orleans convention; Vicksburg convention; Nashville convention, undated (Box 96)
      - New Orleans Daily Picayune, 1878 (Box 96)
      - New Orleans, the Southwestern Christian Advocate, 1877 Jan.-1880 Oct., notes, and undated (Box 96)
      - New Orleans Times, 1879 (Box 96)
      - New Orleans Weekly Louisianan, undated (Box 96)
      - New York Daily Herald, 1879, and notes, undated (Box 96)
      - New York Globe, undated (Box 96)
      - New York Times, 1878-1879 (Box 96)
      - (NIP), 1972 and undated, 6 writings (Box 96)
      - North Louisiana Journal, St. Joseph, Tensas Parish, undated (Box 96)
      - Notes, circa 1972 (Box 96)
      - Outlines, 1971 and undated; Original thesis and revision (Box 96)
      - Painter, Nell Irvin, Book review: Athearn's In Search of Canaan.. ., JSH, 1978 (Box 96)
      - Philadelphia Christian Recorder, notes, undated (Box 96)
      - Photocopies, 1858-1887, 1906, 1921-1929 (Box 96)
      - Photoduplication Service, Library of Congress, Washington D.C., correspondence, 1972 (Box 96)
      - Posters, 1976 and undated, 2 items (Box 96)
      - Quindaro town site (Kansas), articles, 1987 (Box 96)
      - Race, Class and Politics in Black South, 1971 (Box 97)
      - Reactions in Kansas, undated (Box 97)
      - Reactions in the South, undated (Box 97)
      - Relief for Exodusters, undated (Box 97)
      - Report of the Committee of the Senate upon the relations between labor and capital, and testimony taken by the committee, 1885 (Box 97)
      - Senate Reports (by number and topic)
        - 693, 1880 (Box 97)
        - 693-Part II, preliminary index completed, circa 1880 (Box 97)
        - 693, II and III, undated (Box 97)
        - 855, I, Louisiana, Caddo Parish, 1879 (Box 97)
        - 855, I, Louisiana, Tensas Parish (Fairfax), Concordia Parish (Young), 1879 (Box 97)
        - 855, Louisiana: Natchitoches Parish, St. Mary's Parish, Pointe Coupee Parish, Blount or Blunt, 1879 (Box 97)
        - 855, Mississippi, 1879 (Box 97)
      - Shreveport Evening Standard, undated (Box 97)
      - Singleton, Benjamin-Senate Report 693, and Kansas Historical Society, undated (Box 97)
      - Singleton, Pap, and economic conditions, undated (Box 97)
      - Singleton scrapbook transcriptions and National Archives letters, undated (Box 97)
      - Soul Murder and Slavery, U.S. History as Women's History, [Professional Papers], (NIP), 1995 (Box 97)
      - St. Louis Globe Democrat
        - 1879 Jan-1879 Mar. (Box 97)
        - 1879 Apr., notes, circa 1972 (Box 97)
        - 1879 May-Dec., notes, undated (Box 97)
      - Tally Sheets, 693 III, undated (Box 97)
      - Teller Committee Report, 1879 Feb. 27, and recommendations (Box 97)
      - Tennessee collections, undated (Box 97)
      - Tennessee State Library and Archives, newspapers and Nashville city directory, 1867, 1879, and undated (Box 98)
      - Texas Newspapers: 1879-1880, Eugene C. Barker, Texas History Center Newspaper Collection, Austin, notes, circa 1972 (Box 98)
      - Texas newspapers, 1879-1880, notes, circa 1972 (Box 98)
      - Texas, Oklahoma, and Liberia, 1946-1957, 5 writings (Box 98)
      - Texas State Archives and Texas State Secretary of State Papers, 1880, and notes, circa 1972 (Box 98)
      - Topeka Weekly Commonwealth, undated (Box 98)
      - Union Pacific/Kansas Pacific Railroad, circa 1972 (Box 98)
      - University of Texas at Austin, newspaper reproduction request, 1972 (Box 98)
      - University of Texas, newspapers- Dallas Herald, 1880 (Box 98)
      - Vicksburg Daily Commercial, 1877-1879 (Box 98)
      - Weekly Louisianan and New York Times, Lamont Document Room, 1878-1881 (Box 98)
      - WPA slave narratives, Library of Congress, undated (Box 98)
      - Uncategorized notes and miscellaneous printed materials, 1972-1973 and undated, Folders 1-5 of 11 (Box 98)
      - Uncategorized notes and miscellaneous printed materials, 1972-1973 and undated, Folders 6-11 of 11 (Box 99)
  - History of White People Subseries, 2005-2007, 1 box
    Drafts of several chapters; also contains a lecture in which Painter addresses her themes and approaches in this work. These previously closed materials are now open following upon the book's publication in 2010.
    - Drafts, chapters 2, 5, and 6, 2005-2006, 2 folders (Box 260)
    - America through French Eyes: Alexis de Tocqueville and Gustave de Beaumont, Hayes/Robinson Lecture, Royal Holloway College of the University of London, 2007 Mar. 16 (Box 260)
  - Hosea Hudson Subseries, 1931-1996 and undated, bulk 1976-1982, 8 boxes
    Contains correspondence, readers' reports, drafts, interview transcripts, and research materials for The Narrative of Hosea Hudson: His Life as a Negro Communist in the South (1979), as well as related talks and articles by Painter.
    Materials have been divided into three subgroups: Correspondence, Drafts, and Research Materials. The Correspondence subgroup largely consists of publication-related materials and correspondence between Painter and Hudson, which began in 1976 and lasted through 1982. Many of Hudson's letters contain newspaper articles that he routinely clipped, typed notes onto, and attached to the letter. Other items of note in the subgroup include readers' reports and Painter's replies to them and a letter of consignment for the Hudson interview tapes, which Painter donated to the Southern Oral History Program at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, where they are housed in the Southern Historical Collection.
    The Research Materials subgroup largely consists of materials used in verifying and annotating the text. Hudson's FBI file is of particular interest. Also contained are several interview transcripts and related articles and talks by Painter, including her talk at UNC, How I Wrote Hosea Hudson.
    The materials contained in the Correspondence and Research Materials subgroups have been organized alphabetically. The folder titles for articles or talks by Painter begin with the work's title, followed by (NIP). Folder titles for works by other others are organized by author, last name first. The materials in the Drafts subgroup are organized chronologically.
    - Correspondence (Box 99)
      - 1977-1978 (Box 99)
      - 1978-1980 and 2 photos, Painter and Hudson, undated (Box 99)
      - Book reviews of Hosea Hudson, 1979-1982 (Box 99)
      - Donald, Aida and Harvard University Press, 1978 (Box 99)
      - Harvard University Press publication requirements, 1979 (Box 99)
      - Hudson, 1980-1982 (Box 99)
      - Hudson, 1981-1982 (Box 100)
      - Hudson and Harvard University Press, 1978-1979 (Box 100)
      - Hudson-Painter, 1976-1978, 2 folders (Box 100)
      - Kathy, notes on Hudson's speech, 1977 (Box 100)
      - Miscellaneous, 1977-1986, 6 folders (Box 100)
      - Murphy, Al, 1977-1978 (Box 101)